Margaret Waring Buck Papers
© 2005 University of Connecticut
Margaret Waring Buck Papers.
undated, circa 1860-1993.
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center.
Buck, Margaret Waring.
6 linear feet.
Margaret Waring Buck was born in New York in 1905. She was an illustrator, naturalist, and physiognomist who lived much of her life in Mystic, Connecticut, up until her death in 1997. Miss Buck studied the 'science' of Face Reading with Dr. Holmes W. Merton in the 1930s in New York City. Miss Buck also illustrated many books on natural subjects, including Animals Through the Year, published in 1941, and How They Grow, published in 1972. Margaret Waring Buck died on 13 March 1997.
MSS19970034
Biography
Margaret Waring Buck was born in New York in 1905. She was an illustrator, naturalist, and physiognomist who lived much of her life in Mystic, Connecticut, until her death in 1997. Miss Buck studied the 'science' of Face Reading with Dr. Holmes W. Merton in the 1930s in New York City. These techniques are elaborated by Miss Buck in The Face - What it Means: The Merton Method of Character Analysis, published in 1979. Miss Buck also illustrated many books on natural subjects, including Animals Through the Year, published in 1941, and How They Grow, published in 1972. Margaret Waring Buck died on 13 March 1997.
Scope and Content
Margaret Waring Buck has produced a number of self-illustrated books explaining how animals live in the wild. The typical Buck nature book contains detailed black-and-white drawings of the plants, animals, insects and birds to be found in a particular outdoors location, along with an explanatory text ideal for young naturalists who are beginning to learn about the subject.
The collection includes manuscript materials and original artwork by Miss Buck for The Face - What it Means, and for several of Miss Buck's nature books, including Along the Seashore and How They Grow. Collection also includes a wide range of Miss Buck's personal papers and memorabilia, including a large number of photographs, many dating back to the 1800s. The collection contains images or information on the following families: Buck, Atwater, Waring and Pratchett. Notebooks and newspaper clippings from the 1990-93 period are also present.
Arrangement
Series I: Personal Papers ( undated, 1889-1993 )
Series II: Correspondence ( undated, 1909-1993 )
Series III: Publications ( undated, circa 1860-1978 )
Series IV: Notes and Sketches ( undated, 1946-1983 )
Series V: Photographs ( undated, circa 1870-1993 )
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of materials pertaining to children's literature and associated artwork, as well as natural history materials. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the reference desk.
Separated Material
The following materials have been separated from the collection and cataloged:
Along the Seashore(3 editions) c. 1964 Dodd Call No. CLC C611
Animals Through the Year(2 editions) c. 1941 Dodd Call No. CLC C612
Buck Immigrants and Worldwide Descendants c. 1989 Dodd Call No.
Country Boy(3 editions) c. 1947 Dodd Call No.
The Face - What it Means(3 copies) c. 1979 Dodd Call No.
How They Grow c. 1972 Dodd Call No. CLC C613
In Ponds and Streams(2 editions)c. 1955 Dodd Call No.
In Woods and Fields(3 editions) c. 1950 Dodd Call No. CLC C614
In Yards and Gardens(2 editions) c. 1952 Dodd Call No. CLC C534
Pets from the Pond c. 1958 Dodd Call No.
Small Pets from Woods and Fields c. 1960 Dodd Call No. CLC C615
Where They Go in Winter(2 editions) c. 1968 Dodd Call No. CLC C616
Bibliography
Writings by the Author
Animals Through the Year Rand McNally, 1941.
Country Boy, Abingdon (Nashville), 1947.
In Woods and Fields, Abingdon, 1950.
In Yards and Gardens, Abingdon, 1952.
In Ponds and Streams, Abingdon, 1955.
Pets from the Pond, Abingdon, 1958.
Small Pets from Woods and Fields, Abingdon, 1960.
Along the Seashore, Abingdon, 1964.
Where They Go in Winter, Abingdon, 1968.
How They Grow, Abingdon, 1972.
The Face - What it Means: The Merton Method of Character Analysis, Libra, 1979.
Periodicals
Atlantic June, 1955.
Booklist, June 1, 1947; March 15, 1950; April 1, 1952; April 15, 1955.
Bookmark, April, 1950; May, 1952.
Book Week, May 10, 1964, p. 33.
Chicago Sun Book Week, May 25, 1947, p. 5.
Chicago Sunday Tribune, April 23, 1950, p. 16; April 27, 1952, p. 14.
Christian Science Monitor, April 29, 1950, p. 6; May 15, 1952, p. 10; May 12, 1955, p. 11; May 7, 1964, p. B9.
Cleveland Open Shelf, May, 1950.
Commonweal, May 22, 1964.
Horn Book, May, 1950; April, 1952; April, 1955.
Kirkus, March 15, 1947; February 15, 1950; February 15, 1952; February 1, 1955.
Library Journal, April 15, 1947; May 1, 1950; May 1, 1952; May 15, 1955; April 15, 1964.
New York Herald Tribune Book Review, April 27, 1947, p. 8; April 9, 1950, p. 8; April 6, 1952, p. 8; May 15, 1955.
New York Times, May 11, 1947, p. 22; March 5, 1950, p. 22; June 8, 1952, p. 30; July 24, 1955, p. 18.
Saturday Review, May 10, 1952; May 14, 1955.
Saturday Review of Literature, March 11, 1950.
Springfield Republican, September 14, 1947, p. B5; March 26, 1950.
Index Terms
This record series is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Subjects:
Illustration of books—20th century.; Illustrated children's books—20th century.; Physiogynomy.; Natural history literature—United States.; Family—Atwater, Buck, Waring, Pratchett
Document Types:
Correspondence.; Personal Papers.; Manuscripts.; Notebooks.; Publications.; Photographs.; Artwork.; Daguerotypes.
Occupations:
Illustrator.; Naturalist.; Physiognomist.
Restrictions on Access
There are no access restrictions on this collection.
Acquisition Information
Material donated to Archives & Special Collections by Barbara W. Hood and Margaret W. Buck.
Detailed Description
- Series I: Personal Papers, undated, 1889-1993
  - Address books, undated (Box 1:, Folder 1)
  - Autograph book (Mary Atwater), circa1889 (Box 1:, Folder 2)
  - Book of Common Prayer (Addie Buck), circa 1865 (Box 1:, Folder 3)
  - Book of Common Prayer (Mary Atwater), circa 1904 (Box 1:, Folder 4)
  - Clippings (Box 1:, Folder 5)
  - Daybooks, 1966-1977 (Box 1:, Folder 6)
  - Daybooks, 1978-1985 (Box 1:, Folder 7)
  - Daybooks, 1987-1993 (Box 1:, Folder 8)
  - Doll sketches, undated (Box 1:, Folder 9)
  - Financial Records, undated (Box 1:, Folder 10)
  - Personal Papers, 1905-1961 (Box 1:, Folder 11)
- Series II: Correspondence, undated, 1909-1993
  - General, 1943-1993 (Box 1:, Folder 12)
  - Buck, Margaret, undated, 1909 (Box 1:, Folder 13)
  - Buck, Margaret “Peggie”, undated (Box 1:, Folder 14)
  - Mary to Mother/Mother to Mary, undated (Box 1:, Folder 15)
  - Gergerian, Edmund, 1978 (Box 1:, Folder 16)
  - Knowles, E., undated (Box 1:, Folder 17)
- Series III: Publications, undated, 1860-1978
  - Books
  - Along the Seashore (Box 1:, Folder 18)
    - Original art, circa 1964; 2 items (Box 4)
  - Animals Through the Year (Box 1:, Folder 19)
  - Country Boy (Box 1:, Folder 20)
  - The Face--What it Means (Box 1:, Folder 21)
    - Copyright Information, 1974-1978 (Box 1:, Folder 22)
    - Phrenological Character certificate, 1860 (Box 1:, Folder 23)
    - Illustrations--original art and mss., circa 1970s (Box 3)
    - Mounted illustrations, circa 1979 (Box 3)
    - Promotional artwork, mounted, circa 1979 (Box 3)
    - E. Hemingway pencil sketch, with notes, circa 1979 (Box 3)
  - How They Grow (Box 1:, Folder 24)
    - Award, 1972 (Box 1:, Folder 25)
    - Mounted original art, circa 1972; 7 items (Box 4)
    - Original art, circa 1972; 11 items (Box 4)
  - In Ponds and Streams (Box 1:, Folder 26)
    - Original art, circa 1955; 2 items (Box 4)
  - In Woods and Fields (Box 1:, Folder 27)
  - In Yards and Gardens (Box 1, Folder 28:)
    - Original art, circa 1952; 2 items (Box 4)
  - Pets from the Pond (Box 1:, Folder 29)
    - Original art), circa 1958; 2 items (Box 4)
  - Small Pets from Woods and Fields (Box 1:, Folder 30)
    - Original art, circa 1960; 2 items (Box 4)
  - Where They Go in Winter (Box 1:, Folder 31)
    - Original art, most mounted, circa 1968; 14 items (Box 4)
  - Other Publications
  - Greeting cards, 1945-1951 (Box 1:, Folder 32)
  - Poems, 1927-1974 (Box 4:, Folder 33)
  - Publications (magazines, etc.), 1943-1953 (Box 3)
- Series IV: Notes and Sketches, undated, 1946-1983
  - Brain, 1963-1983 (Box 1:, Folder 34)
  - History, undated (Box 1:, Folder 35)
  - History of Physiognomy, undated (Box 1:, Folder 36)
  - [Science], undated (Box 1:, Folder 37)
  - Large sketchbook (pencil figure studies), undated (Box 3)
  - Notebook - 'Floral Sketches', circa 1968 (Box 3)
  - Notebook - 'Mouse Sketches', circa 1966 (Box 3)
  - Notebook - 'Nature Sketches', circa 1971 (Box 3)
  - Colored pencil sketch (Mystic, Conn.?), 1968 (Box 3)
  - Unidentified art, pencil sketches, circa 1946-76 (Box 3)
- Series V: Photographs, undated, circa 1850-1993
  - Subseries A: Cased Photographs, [1850s]-1862
    - William Pratchett, daguerrotype, union case, [1850s] (Box 6:, Other 1997-0034.ph1)
    - William Pratchett, daguerrotype, union case, contains lock of hair, [1850s] (Box 6:, Other 1997-0034.ph8)
    - Dr. William Atwater, daguerrotype, case missing, [1855?] (Box 6:, Other 1997-0034.ph6)
    - Sally Waring, ambrotype, case missing, [late 1850s] (Box 6:, Other 1997-0034.ph7)
    - Margaret M. Waring, daguerrotype, wood/leather case, 1855 July 15 (Box 6:, Other 1997-0034.ph9)
    - Margaret M. Waring [Maggie], daguerrotype, wood/leather case, 1855 August 4 (Box 6:, Other 1997-0034.ph5)
    - Margaret Waring Atwater, daguerrotype, wood/leather case, [late 1850s] (Box 6:, Other 1997-0034.ph10)
    - Margaret Waring Atwater, daguerrotype, wood/leather case, [circa 1860] (Box 6:, Other 1997-0034.ph11)
    - Great Grandmother Waring, daguerrotype, wood/leather case, [1850s] (Box 6:, Other 1997-0034.ph12)
    - [Great Grandmother Waring], ambrotype, case missing, [1850s] (Box 6:, Other 1997-0034.ph13)
    - Aunt Ann Goggill (West), ambrotype, wood/leather case, 1858 December (Box 6:, Other 1997-0034.ph3)
    - Albert Atwater, ambrotype, wood/leather case, 1862 January 28 (Box 6:, Other 1997-0034.ph4)
    - Albert Atwater, ambrotype, wood/leather case, 1862 July 24 (Box 6:, Other 1997-0034.ph2)
  - Subseries B: Prints, 1870s-1990
    - Atwater, Margaret Waring, copy [see cased photograph 1997-0034.ph11], [circa 1860] (Box 2)
    - [Great Grandmother Waring,] tintype, [1870s?] (Box 2)
    - Collins, Minna Pratchett, circa 1900 (Box 2)
    - Ancigas, Josephine and Paul, [1890s?] (Box 2)
    - Atwater, Mary and Charles Buck, photographs and wedding invitation, 1904-1905 (Box 2)
    - Waring, Margaret, 1908 (Box 2)
    - Atwater [Mother and Grandmother], [Burlington]; Aunt Cornelia (Mrs. Edward Daniel), West Indies, 1920s (Box 2)
    - Mary and Charlie, 1959-1961 (Box 2)
    - Mary, 1953-1969 (Box 2)
    - Dolls by Mary Buck and Clara Atwater, [1940s] (Box 2)
    - Atwater, Clara and dolls, 1946 (Box 2)
    - Buck, Margaret Waring, age 5 months-22 years, 1905-1927 (Box 2)
    - [Buck, Margaret Waring], 1946 November (Box 3)
    - Vermont Vacation [New Hampshire], [1930s-1940s] (Box 2)
    - Buck, Charles A., photo by daughter Margaret Waring Buck, about 1950 (Box 3)
    - Buck, Margaret W., 1950s (Box 2)
    - Unidentified photographs, 1958-1961 (Box 2)
    - Unidentified family or friends, undated (Box 2)
    - Photo album photos, Margaret W. Buck, 1959, 1961 (Box 2)
    - [Margaret Waring Buck with book display], Willimantic, Conn., 1966 March 9 (Box 3)
    - Photo album photos, [1975 December] (Box 2)
    - Photo album photos, MWB, 1977 [February 1976] (Box 2)
    - Photo album photos, MWB, 1978 March 24 (Box 2)
    - Photo album photos, 1978-1979 (Box 2)
    - Photo album photos, 1981 (Box 2)
    - Photo album photos, MWB, 1982 (Box 2)
    - Photo album photos, MWB, 1984 (Box 2)
    - Photo album photos, MWB, 1985 (Box 2)
    - Photo album photos, MWB, Aaron Jamison Buck and Barbara, 1986 November 16 (Box 2)
    - Photo album photos, MWB, 1990 (Box 2)
    - Photo album photos, 1993 (Box 2)
    - Photo album photos, MWB, Christmas, undated (Box 2)
    - Photo album photos, undated (Box 2)
    - Family photographs: Aaron 6 yrs, Alicia 2 ½ yrs, undated, 1992 (Box 2)
    - Camden, Wiscasset, ME, undated (Box 2)
    - Book photographs, undated (Box 2)
    - Publicity photographs, undated (Box 2)
    - Landscapes, building, gardens, undated (Box 2)
    - Slides: Landscapes, birds, trees, animals, undated (Box 2)
    - Photograph album, 1903-1956 (Box 2)
  - Subseries C: Negatives, transparencies and slides, undated, 1952-1955
    - Black and White negatives (Box 7)
      - Bats, undated
      - Buck, Mary Atwater, undated
      - Canada geese and young, undated
      - Cat, undated
      - Dolls, undated
      - Egg flowers, 1955 April
      - Flowers, undated
      - Frogs and Henry turtle, 1952 September
      - Garden, undated
      - Insects, undated
      - Landscapes, undated
      - Adult mallards, undated
      - Mallard sitting, undated
      - Publicity photos, undated
      - Shrew, undated
      - Swan, undated
      - Unidentified group, undated
      - Unidentified portraits, undated
      - Adult wood duck and young, undated
    - Color transparencies (Box 7)
      - Landscapes, undated
    - Color slides (Box 7)
      - Landscapes, geese, undated
  - Cartes-de-visite albums, [1860s?] (Box 5)